<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning the antiquity of the people of God, called Quakers their worship, their mother, new and heavenly Jerusalem, their faith, and who is the author and finisher of it ... the Church of Christ's prayer, and in what, their cross, and their baptism / by G.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40147</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12182132</idno>
  <idno type="VID">55696</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240950440</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1314</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12182132</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 890:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning the antiquity of the people of God, called Quakers their worship, their mother, new and heavenly Jerusalem, their faith, and who is the author and finisher of it ... the Church of Christ's prayer, and in what, their cross, and their baptism / by G.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Fox. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55696:1"/>
            <p>Concerning the ANTIQUITY OF THE <hi>People of God,</hi> CALLED QUAKERS; THEIR <hi>Worship;</hi> Their <hi>Mother, New</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Jerusalem;</hi> Their <hi>Faith,</hi> and who is the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Finisher</hi> of it; Their <hi>Belief;</hi> Their <hi>VVay;</hi> Their <hi>Original;</hi> Their <hi>Hope,</hi> distinct from the <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> that Perishes; Their <hi>Gospel;</hi> The <hi>True Ministers;</hi> Their <hi>Leader</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> and that which gives them <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> Their <hi>Mediator;</hi> Their <hi>Overseer;</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ's Prayer,</hi> and in <hi>what;</hi> Their <hi>Cross;</hi> and Their <hi>Baptism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>G. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb facs="tcp:55696:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55696:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>I.</hi> Concerning the Antiquity of our Worship.</head>
            <p>IT is that which Christ set up above 1600 years ago, which, when he put down the Jews Worship at the Temple at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem;</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Worship at the Mountain of <hi>Jacobs</hi> VVell; saying, <hi>The Hour cometh and now is, they that Worship the Father, must worship him in the Spirit and in the Truth.</hi> And this VVorship <hi>in the Spirit and in the Truth,</hi> is above all the VVill-worshipers, and Dragon-worshipers, and the VVorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Beast: for God hath poured out of his Spirit upon all Flesh, and Grace and Truth is come by Jesus; and this Spirit and Truth is in the Hearts and inward parts of People, that with this Spirit of Truth they may know the God of Truth; and in the Spirit of Truth, serve and worship the God of Truth; which pure Truth and Holy Spirit, the Devil, the soul Spirit, and all his VVorshippers, are out of, and cannot come into, for there is no Truth in him. And this is our pure and perfect standing VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which Christ the Son of God set up above 1600 years ago.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>II.</hi> Concerning the Antiquity of our Religion.</head>
            <p>WHich was set up by Christ in his Apostles, above 1600 years ago, who saith, <hi>That pure Religion and undefiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God is this, to visit the Widdows and the Fatherless; and to keep themselves unspotted from the World.</hi> And this pure undefiled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which brings to visit the VVidows and the Fatherless, is above all the unpure, vain, defiled Religions, that do not bridle Peoples Tongues, nor keep them from the Spots of the VVorld: and their VVidows and their Fatherless go a Begging about the Streets, and not taken in, Fed, nor Cloathed, nor visited. And this is below the pure undefiled Christian Religion, that was set up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the primitive Christians, in the Apostles daies, which is our pure undefiled Religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55696:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>III.</hi> Concerning the Antiquity of our Mother, New and Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SHE is the same as She was confest to by the Apostles, in the primitive times, above 1600 years ago, who said <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that is below is in Bondage with her Children, but <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that is above is free, which is the Mother of us all; which is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the true Believers in the Light; the Life in Christ, who walk in the Light of Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem</hi> their Mother. And they that receive Christ to them, he gives Power to become the Sons of God. And so are the Children of Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem, The Bride, the Lambs Wife, which is free;</hi> as in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.25. And the Apostle saith to the Church of Christ, the <hi>Hebrews, Ye are come to Heavenly</hi> Jerusalem; <hi>and to the innumerable company of Angels; and to the Assembly and Congregation of the First Born, which are written in Heaven; and to God the Judge of all; And to the Spirits of just men made perfect;</hi> Heb. 12.22.23.</p>
            <p>Now here you may see, that the Saints were come in the Apostles daies to <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem</hi> their Mother; and to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Company of Angels; And to the Spirits of just men made perfect; And to the Congregation of the First Born, written in Heaven, while they were upon the Earth And this <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem</hi> that is free, is the true Mother of all the true Christians now: for us all by Nature are Born Natural, so all the true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Christ are Born again; for he that Believes, is Born of God, fo Born Spiritually, and such are Heavenly <hi>Jerusalems Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> saw this Holy and Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> descending out of Heaven, from God, prepared as a Bride Adorned for her Husband; and there shall enter into it no unclean thing, nor whatsoever worketh Abomination, or maketh a Lye; but they which are written in the Lambs Book of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.27.</p>
            <p>Now here you may see, here is three Witnesses or Testimonies that do confirm <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> that is above and free, to be the Mother of us all, that Believe in Christ and receive him, to whom He hath given them power to become the Sons of God and Children of the Light, by Believing in His Light, and Children
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55696:3"/> of the Day: And so this Spiritual Birth knows <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem</hi> their Mother, and walk in the Light of their Mother, <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> whose Light is the Lord God and the Lamb. Now this <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> our Mother, comes down from Heaven, that brings forth her Free-born Children; and the power and Light is from Christ, who is from above; through whose power and Light they become Children of God, and Children of the Light, and of <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> where there is no Night; and so are Nursed up in the Arms and Bosome of <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> their Mother, who Feeds them with Milk of the Word, and they grow by it.</p>
            <p>For the Lord saith, <hi>The Law shall go out of</hi> Sion, <hi>and the word of the Lord from</hi> Jerusalem. <hi>Micah,</hi> 4.2. Is not this Heavenly <hi>Sion,</hi> and Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> And that the Word shall not depart out of the Mouths of Heavenly <hi>Jerusalems</hi> Seed and Children: yea, not out of the Mouth of its Seed Seed, but the word of power, and of Patience, and of Wisdom, shall abide in the Mouth of its Seed Seed; namely, all Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> our Mothers Spiritual Children in the New Covenant, and New Testament, which can not joyn to, nor own any Mother Church below her that is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly. And here is the Antiquity of our Mother acknowledged, to be the Mother of all true Christians in the Apostles Days, and now. And in our Mother Heavenly <hi>Jerusalems</hi> Children, is Love of Loves, and Joy of Joyes; above all Joyes and Loves below, that will pass away.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>IV.</hi> Now concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> from whence we have our <hi>Faith,</hi> and who is the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisher</hi> of it.</head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith to the Church of Christ, the <hi>Hebrews; Let us run with patience the Race that is set before us; Looking unto JESUS, the Author and Finisher of our Faith.</hi> Heb. 12.1.2.</p>
            <p>Now here you may see the Apostles did not make the Saints a Faith, but bid them look unto <hi>JESUS,</hi> who was the Author, or Beginner and Finisher of their Divine, Holy and Precious Faith; the Mystery of which is held in a pure Conscience: And so <hi>Christ</hi> doth reveal His Faith to His People; and so they grow in Faith, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55696:4"/> from Faith to Faith up unto Christ, the Author and Finisher of it. So the Apostle did not say to the Saints, the Church of Christ, look unto us to make you a Faith, and that they should be the Author and Finisher of their Faith, for them; but bid them look unto Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, the Author and Finisher of their Faith: and so this was the Apostles Doctrine to the <hi>Christians</hi> in the <hi>primitive Times,</hi> above 1600 Years ago; and this is the Doctrine that we have received and own, who do look at none below Jesus Christ, to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Finisher of our Holy, Precious and Divine Faith; in which Faith all God's People please him, and have access to him; which Faith is our Victory over that which displeases God, and in which Holy Faith, is our Holy Unity, and by this Precious Faith, all the Just Live; and this is the One, Holy, Pure, Precious, and Divine Faith, that purifies the Hearts of God's People, which Christ is the Author and Finisher of; in which they have access to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, and serve and please Him. So our Holy, Divine, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or Universal Faith, Christ is the Beginner, or Author and Finisher of; in which Holy Faith the Church of Christ did, and do Build one another up in, which (as before) Christ the Holy One, is the Author and Finisher of, and not Men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>V.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Belief.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHRIST, the Heavenly Man, and Second <hi>Adam,</hi> doth En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every One that comes into the World, with His Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Spiritual Light, which is the Life in him, the Word, and by Him the Word, all things were Made and Created: and Christ saith, <hi>Believe in the Light, that you may become Children of the Light.</hi> And so we Believing in the Light, the Life in Christ, are become Children of the Light, and so are grafted into him, the Life, in whom we have the Light of Life, and so are past from the death in <hi>Adam,</hi> to the Life in <hi>CHRIST,</hi> the Second <hi>Adam;</hi> and as the Apostle saith, <hi>He that Believes, is Born of God, and overcomes the World:</hi> and these are the true and living Members; or the living Stones that make up the Spiritual Houshold, the Church of <hi>Christ,</hi> which He is the Holy Head of; and as the Apostle saith, <hi>It is giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to Believe;</hi> so <hi>Christ</hi> hath given us a Light, which is the Life in himself; and saith believe in the Light; so we Believe in that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55696:4"/> which Christ hath given us, and commandeth and teacheth us to Believe in, namely, the Light, which is the Life in Him, by which we may see him and know him, and that we may become Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light, and of the Day of Christ; and this Light shin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Hearts, it gives us, the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Christ Jesus: and this is the Treasure which we have in our Earthen Vessels; and after we do Believe, we are seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God's Spirit, and can set to our Seal, having the Witness in our selves that God is true in all his Promises, and Prophets, and Types and Shadows in the Law, concerning his Son Christ Jesus, in whom we do Believe, who is our Heavenly Rock and Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Build upon in his Heavenly Divine Light; and all the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations that Men lay below Christ, we cannot Build upon; for we Believe in the Light, the Life in Christ, and are grafted into him: <hi>And Christ saith, He that Believeth in Me hath Eternal Life: And they that do the Work of God, Believe in the Son God that he hath sent; and be that Believeth shall not perish, but hath Everlasting Life.</hi> And Christ said to <hi>Martha, He that Believeth, though he were Dead, yet shall he Live; and he that Liveth and Believeth shall never Dye.</hi> This is the True and Living Belief, that Christ hath taught us: and he hath given us his Light to Believe in; which Belief is Distinct from all false Beliefs that Men make and teach.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>VI.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Way.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHRIST JESUS Said, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life; no Man cometh to the Father, but by Me.</hi> John 14.6.</p>
            <p>So Christ is the New and Living Way, which God hath Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated for us, as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.20. And this New and Living VVay Christ set up Himself, above 1600 Years ago, by which we come to God. And as <hi>David</hi> said; <hi>As for God, His Way is perfect; and it is God that Girdeth me with His Strength, and maketh my Way perfect.</hi> Psal. 18.30, 32.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>David</hi> saith, <hi>Wherewith shall a Young Man cleanse his Way, by taking heed according to Thy Word.</hi> Psal. 119.9. So the <hi>Word</hi> will keep out of Defiled VVays.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55696:5"/>
            <p>And as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>The Way or Path of the Just is a shining Light, which shines more and more unto the perfect Day.</hi> Prov. 4.18. <hi>But the Way of the Wicked is Darkness, and they know not at what they Stumble.</hi> And that is the Condition of them that hath the Light. <hi>The Just Man's Way or Path, and the Way of the Just is Uprightness; and Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> most Upright God, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the path of the Just.</hi> Jsa. 26.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And you that have been astray from the Light, have not you heard the Word from behind you say, This is the Way, walk in it,</hi> Jsa. 30.21.</p>
            <p>And all you that have heard the Word Christ, and so turned to him, the Light, and the Way; you know the Scripture fulfilled, the <hi>Old Testament</hi> was the good old Way sor the <hi>Jews</hi> to walk in; but <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> is the New and Living Way to God, to them that Believe and Walk in him; for God hath given Christ to be a Governour and Leader for his People and to be his Salvation to the ends of the Earth; So Christ, who is our Leader, is our Counsellour and Salvation, and Way to God, and there is no other Way to the Father, but by Him, who hath Dyed for our Sins, and is Risen for our Justification.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <head>VII. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Original.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOHN</hi> saith, <hi>In the Beginning was the word,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And all things were made by the word; and without the word was not any thing made, that was made.</hi> John 1.9. <hi>And the Apostles were Preachers of the word.</hi> Acts 15.25. and 9.9. And the Apostle said, <hi>the Word is nigh thee, in thy Heart and in thy Mouth; and this is the word of Faith which we Preach.</hi> Rom. 10.8. And <hi>James</hi> saith, <hi>of his own Will begat He us, by the word of Truth,</hi> James. 1.18.</p>
            <p>So God's People are begotten by the Word of Truth, being Born again, nor of Corruptible Seed, but of Incorruptible, by the Word of God, which lives, and abides, and endures forever; and so as new Born Babes desire the sincere Milk of the Word, that they may grow thereby. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 23. and 22.</p>
            <p>And <hi>John</hi> saith, <hi>That which was from the Beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our Eyes, and our Hands have handled of the Word of Life;</hi> That <hi>Declare we unto you, that ye also might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55696:5"/> have Fellowship with us; and truly our Fellowship is with the Father and his Son, Jesus Christ.</hi> 1 John, 1.1.2, 3. And this Word is no new Commandment; for <hi>John</hi> saith, <hi>I Write no new Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto you, but an Old Commandment, which you had from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: The Old Commandment is the Word, which ye have heard from the Beginning.</hi> 1. John, 2.7. <hi>And by the Word of God, which did abide in the Saints, they overcame the Wicked One,</hi> 1. John, 2.14. <hi>And</hi> John <hi>bore Record of the Word of God,</hi> Rev. 1.2. And said Christ's Name was called the Word of God, and the Word is called the Word of Grace, and the Word of Faith, and the Word of Wisdom, and the Word of Power, and the Word of Patience; and this is the Word by which all God's People are Sanctified and made clean; and by it all things are Sanctified to them, and by this Word they are reconciled to God, and this Word was before the Confusion of <hi>Babel,</hi> with their many Languages, which the Priests and the VVorld called the Original. And <hi>Pilate</hi> set a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perscription, in Letters of <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> upon <hi>Christ,</hi> when they Crucified him: And the Beast, and the VVhore, and the false Church, had power over the Natural Tongues and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. and 17.15. But the VVord of God was before their Tongues and Languages were; and Natural Men with their Natural Arts and Sciences, and Tongues, do not know the things of God; for Natural Men, in their Natural Schools, may learn their natural Arts and Sciences, and their Natural Tongues, and their Natural Religions, and so be Natural Ministers: But they that hear Christs Voice, and Learn of Him, and are bred up in His School, are made able Ministers of His Everlasting Word.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>VIII.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our true <hi>Hope,</hi> distinct from the <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> that perishes.</head>
            <p>THE Mystery which hath been hid from ages and generations, is now made manifest to the Saints, which is Christ in you, the Hope of Glory, whom we Preach; warning every Man, and teaching every Man in all Wisdom, that we may present every Man perfect in Christ Jesus. <hi>Colos.</hi> 1.27.28. And every Man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55696:6"/> that hath this Hope in him, purifies himself, even as he is Pure, 1. <hi>John,</hi> 3.3. And we are saved by Hope, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. So that all the Saints may know what is the Hope of their Calling; for we being saved by Hope, are saved by Christ, who is to dwell in our Hearts by Faith; for the Apostle saith, <hi>The Lord Jesus Christ, who is our Hope.</hi> 1. Tim. 1. And we are to hold fast this Hope that is set before us, which we have as an Anchor of the Soul, both sure and stedfast; and it entereth into that which is within the Vail, where the Fore-runner is for us entered in, even Jesus. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18, 19, 20. And blessed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, whch according to His aboundant Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, hath begotten us again unto his lively Hope, by the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Jesus Christ from the Dead, to an Inheritance Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and Undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reserved in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the Saints, which are kept by the power of God through Faith unto Salvation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Here you may see the Saints that are in this True and Living Hope, have an Inheritance Immortal and Undefiled, who are kept by the power of God, through Faith unto Salvation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>IX.</hi> Now concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Gospel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Apostle tells the <hi>Romans, That the Gospel of Christ, is the power of God to every One that Believes: For by the Gospel, the Righteousness of God is revealed, from Faith to Faith; so that the Just shall live by his Faith.</hi> Rom. 1.16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>And again, the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith, <hi>The Gospel which hath been Preached to every Creature under Heaven.</hi> Col 1.23. For Christ said unto His Disciples; <hi>Go ye into all the World, and Preach the Gospel to every Creature.</hi> Mark 16.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And God will judge the Secrets of Mens Hearts by Jesus Christ,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Gospel, saith the Apostle, <hi>He being the Heir of it, that is according to the power of God, which is Preached to every Creature under Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Gospel was Preached to</hi> Abraham, <hi>saying, In thy Seed shall all Nations be Blessed.</hi> And was not this Gospel Preached to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> 430 Years before the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> was given forth? For unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, was the Promise made. He said not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55696:6"/> unto Seeds, as speaking of many, but unto thy Seed, as of one, which Seed is Christ, as in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8.16, 17. So in this Seed Christ, are all Nations and Families of the Earth Blessed: Therefore all Nations and Families of the Earth must come into Christ, the Seed, that bruises the Serpents Head, if they be Blessed, and then they who are of the Seed, through Faith, are Blessed, with Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Abraham.</hi> For the Children of the Promise are counted for the Seed, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. And therefore all Nations and Families of the Earth must come into the Seed, if they be Blessed; and they that be in the Seed, and are Baptized into Christ, have put Him on; and there, in Christ, is neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Greek, Bond</hi> nor <hi>Free, Male</hi> nor <hi>Female,</hi> they are all one in Christ. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.28. And so are all the Sons of God; by Faith in Christ. Now this Everlasting Gospel and Promise was Preached to <hi>Abraham,</hi> 430 Years before the Law was given to <hi>Moses;</hi> saying, <hi>In thy Seed shall all Nations and Families of the Earth be Blessed.</hi> And was it not Preached to <hi>Adam?</hi> when God said, <hi>The Seed of the Woman shall bruise the Serpents Head.</hi> And when Christ came forth, He sent His Disciples into all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to Preach the Gospel to every Creature under Heaven, as before. And <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> who saw the <hi>Night</hi> of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy,</hi> and <hi>Babylons</hi> Fall, saw the <hi>Angel</hi> fly in the midst of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, having the Everlasting Gospel to Preach unto them that dwell on the Earth; and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People; saying with a loud Voice, <hi>Fear God, and give Glory to Him; for the Hour of His Judgment is com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Worship Him that made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea, and Fountains of Water,</hi> Rev. 14.6.7. So this is the Everlasting Gospel, which is Preacht by the Holy Ghost, sent down from Heaven. Now many may have the Letter of the Scripture, and the Form of Holy Mens Words; For the <hi>Jews</hi> had <hi>Abraham</hi>'s, and the Prophets Words, as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians have Christs and the Apostles Words, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> and so may put the Letter for the Gospel; but the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scripture declareth what the Gospel is outward Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures or Letters, may be worn out; but the Gospel is Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is the thing that the Scripture Declareth of; for he that Preacheth any other Gospel (the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith) let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed. For the Gospel, which the <hi>Apostles</hi> Preacht and Taught, was not of Man, neither did they receive it of Men but by the Revelation of Jesus Christ. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. And this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55696:7"/> is the Everlasting Gospel of Life and Salvation; Saying, in thy Seed shall all Nations be Blessed. Now Men may be taught the outward Letter of the Scripture, and receive that from Men in the Natural State; but that which the Scripture, or Letter, Declareth of, is Revealed by Jesus Christ (namely) the Everlasting Gospel, the Seed, in which all Nations are Blessed: and for the Defence of this Gospel were the <hi>Apostles</hi> set, in their Day; and so have I, and many others in our Day and Age; against the Letter-wise Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, as the <hi>Apostles</hi> were against the outward Letter-wise <hi>Jews:</hi> and see what Opposition the Letter-wise made then, and now; that profest the Gospel in VVords, but did, nor do not come into the Seed, in which all are Blessed, and which brings Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to Light, to all them that are in Christ the Seed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>X. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Antiquity <hi>of the</hi> True Ministers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MOses,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> were all sent of God, in the <hi>Old Testament:</hi> and the Lord commanded <hi>Moses</hi> to take Twelve Rods, and write every Man's Name, that were the Heads of the House of their Fathers, upon the Rods, so one Rod for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Prince, according to the House of their Fathers, even twelve Rods; and <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod was among their Rods: and <hi>Moses</hi> laid their Rods before the Lord, in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of <hi>Witness:</hi> and on the Morrow, <hi>Moses</hi> took all the Rods, and <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, for the House of <hi>Levi,</hi> was Budded, and brought forth Budds, and Blossoms, and Ripe Almonds; but the rest of the Heads of <hi>Israels</hi> Rods, brought forth nothing. So the Lord chose the House of <hi>Levy</hi> to serve Him, in the outward <hi>Tabernacle. Numb.</hi> 17. And so the Lord chooseth in His <hi>New Testament</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> whose Spiritual Rods do Bud in the <hi>Inward Tabernacle,</hi> to serve Him in the <hi>Inward Tabernacle,</hi> to be a Holy, Royal Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices to God, by Jesus Christ. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9. And <hi>John,</hi> the greatest Prophet Born of a Woman, was a Man sent from God, <hi>John</hi> 1.6. and <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. And Christ said the Living Father sent Him, as in <hi>John</hi> 6.57. And Christ said, <hi>As thou didst send me into the World, so have I sent them into the World</hi> (namely his Disciples:) and the <hi>Apostles</hi> did Believe that God had sent <hi>Christ,</hi> as in <hi>John</hi> 17.8.18.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55696:7"/>
            <p>And Christ called his Twelve Disciples, and sent them forth to Preach, and gave them Power: and said unto them, freely ye have Received, and freely give, as in <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.1. to the End.</p>
            <p>There you may see how Christ doth Incourage his Free Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and likewise in <hi>Mark</hi> 9. from the 1. to the 6. And Christ said unto his Disciples the Harvest was great, and the Labourers were few; wherefore pray the Lord of the Harvest that he would send forth Labourers, into his Harvest: And so you may see Christ here gives them Power, and they were to Pray to the Lord of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest for Labourers, and not to the High Priests and Rabbies, and the Powers, for them to send forth their Letter to Learned Doctors, and to have Power from them.</p>
            <p>And you may Read in <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. How Christ declareth against the False Teachers; and how that the <hi>Jews</hi> should Persecute, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie, and Scourge, such as Christ sends in their Synagogues, and from City to City: So these False Teachers always persecuted the True. <hi>Mat</hi> 23.30. to the End. And you may see in <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.1. to the 16. How Christ sends forth his Disciples to Call to the Marriage: And when Christ sent forth his Seventy Disciples, he said, <hi>I send you forth as Lambs amongst Wolves, without Bag or Scrip;</hi> and you may see, how he did exhort them, how they should Preach and Behave themselves, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. from the 1. to the 12. And the Apostle told the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> among whom he had been Labouring, for the space of Three Years, and Preached among them; <hi>and he had not ceased to warn every one of them both Night and Day with Tears, and said, I have coveted no Man's Silver, Gold or Apparel; for ye know, That these Hands have Ministred to my Necessities, and to them that were with me: I have shewed you in all Things, how that in so Labouring, ye ought to support the Weak, and do Remember the Words of our Lord Jesus, how that he said, it is a Blessed Thing to Give, rather than to Receive,</hi> Acts, 20.31, 32, 33, 34, 35.</p>
            <p>Here you may see an example of a true Minister, of Christ, and also in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. from the 1. to the 20. How the Apostle there strove to keep the Gospel without Charge, and to make it Free, and how the Apostle Reproves such that did not Labour, that they might Labour and follow the Apostles, whom they had for Examples, as in 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3. who would not be Chargeable to them, as from Vers. 6. to the 13.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55696:8"/>
            <p>And the Apostle said, That Christ ascended on high, and gave Gifts unto Men for the Work of the Ministry; some Apostles, some Prophets, some Evangelists, some Pastors, some Teachers, for the Edifying of the Body of Christ, till we all meet together in the Unity of the Faith, and the Knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, and unto the Measure of the Stature, of the Fulness of Christ; and so to every one of us is given Grace, according to the Measure of the Stature, of the Fulness of Christ, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. from the 1. to the 16.</p>
            <p>Here you may see they had the Gifts from Christ that made them Ministers, and not from Schools and Colledges nor Powers: And <hi>Peter</hi> saith, <hi>Let every Man as he hath received the Gift, Minister the same one to another, as good Stewards of the Manifold Grace of God; and the Elders were to Feed the Flock of God; not by constraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; not for filthy Lucre, but of a willing Mind; not as though you were Lords over God's Heritage, but that you may be Examples to the Flock,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. and 5.2, 3.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. There you may see how the Apostle exhorts them to improve their Gifts, in teaching, and prophecying, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting; and these Gifts they had from Christ.</p>
            <p>And in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. There you may see how the Bishops, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and Overseers; they were not to be given to Wine, nor Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, nor Fighters, nor Covetous, nor given to filthy Lucre; but should be such as could Rule their own Houses well, having their Children in Subjection; for, if they could not Rule their own Houses well, how should they take Care of the Church of God: and likewise, their Wives were to be Honest, not Evil Speakers, but Sober and Faithful in all Things; and so let these Bishops, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Deacons and Ministers first be proved, and if they be found Blameless, then let them Minister, as in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. to the 13. so it seems they were not to Minister, if they were not Blameless in these Things.</p>
            <p>And likewise, you may see the Qualification of the Elder Men, and the Women, that were to be Teachers of good Things, and Teachers of the Younger Women, as in <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. from the first to the 6. And you may see along in the Scriptures, how Christ and the Apostles testified against the Covetous Prophets, Shepherds and Teachers, that Preached for Hire, and Filthy Lucre; and how
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55696:8"/> that the true Prophets, Christ and the Apostles spoke forth freely, and did suffer by the Hirelings, and the Covetous, that Taught for Filthy Lucre.</p>
            <p>And Christ bid his Disciples and Believers to wait at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> until they were indued with Power from on High, and they should Receive the Holy Ghost, and then they should be Witnesses of Christ, both in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and in all <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the utmost Parts of the Earth, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Now, here you may see the Primitive Ordination of Christ's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters; they had their Gifts from Christ, and were indued with Power from on High, and they received the Holy Ghost, and every one was to Minister as they had received the Gift from Christ: so these were not indued with Power from Below, nor from the High Priests, nor Kings, nor Emperors, nor Men, nor Schools, nor Colledges; but they were indued with Power from on High, and their Gifts they had from Christ that ascended on High, above all Principalities, Powers, Thrones and Dominions: so here is the Antiquity, and first Ordination of Christ's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and Teachers, according to the Scripture which we own.</p>
            <p>And God, who poured out of his Spirit upon all Flesh, as in <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. By which, Sons, Daughters, Hand-Maids and Servants, should Prophecy, and have their Spiritual Visions, and Old Men have their Spiritual Dreams: And this now is Witnessed in the Days of the New Covenant, and the Gospel Day of Christ; but they that Rebel against the Spirit of God, and Vex it, and Grieve it, and make a Mock of it; they say, Prophecy, and Revelation, and Visions, are ceased; but the Apostle saith, no Man knows the Things of God, but by the Spirit of God, and the Spirit of God doth Reveal them; and the Natural Man perceiveth not the Things of the Spirit of God, they are Foolishness to him; neither can he know them, because they are Spiritually discerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>XI.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Leader,</hi> and that which gives us <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Lord said, speaking of Christ, in <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.3, 4. I will make an Everlasting Covenant; and behold I will give him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55696:9"/> for a Witness, and a Leader and a Commander to the People; and he shall feed his Flock like a Shepherd, and he shall gather his Lambs in his Arm, and carry them in his Bosom, and gently lead those that are with Young, <hi>Isa.</hi> 40.11. And I will bring the Blind by a way that they knew not, and I will lead them into Paths that they have not known; I will make Darkness Light before them, and Crooked Things Streight: these Things will I do unto them, and not forsake them: <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.16.</p>
            <p>And Christ saith, he is the good Shepherd that lays down his Life for his Sheep; and he calleth his Sheep by Name, and leadeth them, and goes before them; and his Sheep follow him, for they know his Voice, <hi>John</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>And Christ saith, he would send his Believers the Comforter, the Spirit of Truth, which should proceed from the Father, which should guide them, and lead them into all Truth, <hi>John</hi> 15, and 16. Chap. So this was, and is, the Ministers, and Teachers, and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Believers in Christ their Leader, and Guider, into all Truth: For the Apostle saith, That no Prophecy of Scripture came by the Will of Man, neither is it of any private Interpretation; but Holy Men of God, spake forth the Scripture, as they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghost: And so it is the Holy Ghost the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Spirit of Truth, that leads Christ's Believers into all Truth, and into all the Truth of the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>And <hi>John</hi> saith, he that sitteth on the Throne (namely the Lamb) shall dwell among them, and they shall hunger and thirst no more: For the Lamb which is in the midst of the Throne shall feed them, and shall lead them to living Fountains of Water, and God shall wipe away all Tears from their Eyes; they are before the Throne of God, and serve him Night and Day in his Temple, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. to the End.</p>
            <p>That which gave the Church of Christ Knowledg in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Days, gives us, the Church of Christ, Knowledge in our Days: The Apostle saith, God who commanded Light to shine out of Darkness, hath shined in our Hearts, (mark in our Hearts) to give us the Light, of the Knowledg, of the Glory of God, in the Face of Jesus Christ; and we have this Treasure in Earthen Vessels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us; so here we have this Light from God and Christ, and it shines in our Hearts by God's Command, to give us the Knowledge of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55696:9"/> Glory in the Face of Christ his Son; and God hath the Glory and Honour of this Light, which gives us the Knowledg of Christ our Saviour, who is the Treasure of Wisdom and Knowledg; which Light of God and Christ, gives us the Knowledg of the Glory of God, in the Face of Christ (as before) and without this Light we have not the Knowledg of the Glory of God, in the Face of Jesus Christ; as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.7.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>XII.</hi> Now concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Teacher</hi> in the <hi>New Covenant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHRIST saith, <hi>Is it not Written in the</hi> Prophets, <hi>Ye shall be all Taught of God? Every man therefore, that hath Heard and Learned of the Father, cometh unto me; and no Man cometh unto me, except the Father which hath sent me, draw him.</hi> John, 6.44, 45. <hi>All thy Children shall be taught of the Lord; and great shall be the Peace of thy Children, in Righteousness shall they be Established,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 54.13.</p>
            <p>And the Lord said in <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Behold the Day is come, saith the Lord, That I will make a New Covenant with the House of</hi> Israel, <hi>and the House of</hi> Judah; <hi>not according to the Old Covenant, that I made with their Fathers; but this is the Covenant, I will put my Law in their Inward Parts, and write it in their Hearts; and I will be their God, and they shall be my People: and they shall not teach every Man his Neighbour, and every Man his Brother, saying; Know the Lord, for all shall know me from the least to the greatest: So the Old Covenant and his Priests, whose Lips were to preserve Peoples Knowledge, they cease, and there is no need of them in the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; for all shall know God, by the Law he puts in their Minds, and writes in their Hearts,</hi> Heb. 7.8. to the end.</p>
            <p>And this New Covenant, is an Everlasting Covenant, and lasts for ever in all Ages: and all God's People know God and Christ, by the Law he puts in their Minds, and writes in their Hearts, that they need not give Priests Tythes and Maintenance, to teach Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to know the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Apostle saith to the Church of Christ, the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.10. <hi>As touching Brotherly Love, you need not that I write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, for ye your selves are taught of God to love one another.</hi> And <hi>John,</hi> in his General Epistle to the Church of Christ, directs them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55696:10"/> to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Teacher, the Anointing within them; and saith, <hi>Let that therefore abide in you, which you have heard from the Beginning; if that which you have heard from the Beginning shall remain in you, ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so shall continue in the Son, and in the Father: and this is the Promise that he hath promised us, even Eternal Life. And these things have I written unto you, concerning them that Seduce you; but ye have an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing that you have received from him, that abideth in you, and you need not that any Man teach you, but as the same Anointing teaches you, of all things, and is Truth, and is no Lye; and even as it hath taught you, ye shall abide in him.</hi> This <hi>John</hi> writ to the Church of Christ, that had received the Truth, and were established in it.</p>
            <p>Now this Anointing in them, which they have received of God, was the Teacher of his People then, and it is the Teacher of God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Church of Christ now: and the Priests or Teachers, that would seduce from this Anointings teaching within, they would se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them from continuing in the Father, and in the Son, and so from the promise of Eternal Life, as in 1 <hi>John.</hi> 2.21.24.25.26.27.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith to <hi>Titus, The Grace of God, which brings Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, hath appeared unto all Men; Teaching us, that denying Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godliness and Worldly Lusts, we should live Soberly, Righteously, and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in this present World.</hi> Tit. 2.11.12.</p>
            <p>Here you may see what was the Church of Christ's Teacher, the Law in the Heart, the Anointing within, the Grace of God in the Heart, which brings Salvation; it hath appeared unto all Men, to Teach them, and bring their Salvation; if they do not walk de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitefully against the Spirit of Grace, and turn it into Wantonness. And the Lord said unto <hi>Paul, My Grace is sufficient, my Strength is made perfect in Weakness.</hi> 2 Cor. 12.9.10.</p>
            <p>And here is the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Teacher,</hi> which was set up above 1600 Years ago; by which we know God, and continue in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and in the Son, and have Eternal Life; which Grace is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to establish our Hearts, and bring our Salvation: so that we have no need to give the Priests and Hirelings, Tythes and Money to Teach us; for we are come to the Waters of Life, without Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and without Price, which satisfies our Thirsty Souls. <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1.2. &amp; <hi>John.</hi> 7.37. So that we do praise God, and sing <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> through Jesus Christ.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="section">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55696:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>XIII.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of our <hi>Mediatour.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith, <hi>the Law served which was added, because of Transgression till the Seed should Come, to whom the Promise was made,</hi> Gal. 3.19.</p>
            <p>And the Apostle said, God <hi>would have all Men to be saved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth; and</hi> Christ <hi>gave himself a Ransome for all to be testified of in Due time. And there is one</hi> God, <hi>and one</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour <hi>betwixt</hi> God <hi>and Man,</hi> Even <hi>the Man</hi> Christ Jesus, <hi>in</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Now this is the one <hi>Mediatour</hi> which we own betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man; God</hi> having poured his Spirit upon all Flesh, <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> that with the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> they might know <hi>Christ,</hi> the one <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> betwixt them and <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here you may see the <hi>Apostle</hi> did not set up many <hi>Mediatours</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> but one <hi>Mediatour Christ Jesus</hi> the Son of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="section">
            <head>XIV. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Antiquity <hi>of</hi> Over-Seers.</head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith unto the <hi>Elders, and to all the Flock, over the which the</hi> Holy Ghost <hi>hath made you</hi> Over-Seers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Acts, 20.28.</p>
            <p>Here you may see the <hi>Over-Seers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> were not made by <hi>Men;</hi> but the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> made them <hi>Over-Seers.</hi> So they had the Spiritual <hi>Eye</hi> to Watch one over another.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Christ</hi> when he sent forth his Ministers, told them, <hi>that they should be brought before</hi> Magistrates <hi>and</hi> Powers: and said unto them, <hi>take ye no thought how or what things ye shall Answer, or what ye shall Say, for the</hi> Holy Ghost <hi>shall teach you in the same hour, what ye ought to say, as in</hi> Luke, 11.12.</p>
            <p>So here they were to Wait in the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> that led them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all <hi>Truth,</hi> and not to take thought nor follow their own thoughts, but to trust to the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> their Leader and Comforter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="section">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55696:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>XV.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in what.</head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith, <hi>the Spirit helps our Infirmities, we know not what we should pray for as we ought, but the</hi> Spirit <hi>it self Maketh Intercession for us, with</hi> Sighs <hi>and</hi> Groans <hi>that cannot be Uttered; and he that searthes the Heart, knowes what is the Mind of the</hi> Spirit, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he maketh Intercession for the Saints, according to the Will of God,</hi> Rom. 8.26.27. And again the Apostle saith, <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the Understanding; I will sing with the Spirit, I will sing with the Understanding also.</hi> 1 Cor. 14.15. And again, the Apostle <hi>Jude</hi> saith, <hi>Yee Beloved, Build up your selves in the most Holy Faith, praying in the Holy Ghost.</hi> Jude 20.</p>
            <p>Here you may see it is the Spirit that God poureth upon all Flesh, and the Holy Ghost, that the Church of Christ, and all People are to Sing and Pray in, and serve and worship God in; and not to grieve the Spirit of God, nor vex it, nor quench it, nor rebel against it.</p>
            <p>After that God had made Man and Woman in his own Image and Likeness, and Blessed them, and put them in <hi>Paradice;</hi> and gave them a command to Eat of every Tree, except the Tree of Knowledg of Good and Evil; for in the Day they did eat, they should Die: But the Serpent, the lying Spirit, told them they should not Die, if they did eat; and so they followed the Serpents Teaching, and Disobeyed Gods: And therefore God drove them out of <hi>Paradice</hi> into the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you may see how soon a lying false Teacher arose, and Sowed his evil Seed: And <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> for disobeying God, were drove out of <hi>Paradice,</hi> and lost the Image of God, and their blessed Estate.</p>
            <p>And the old World, which grieved the Lord and his Spirit, and corrupted the <hi>Earth,</hi> and filled it with Violence; the Lord said, <hi>His Spirit should not always strive with Man.</hi> So that God brought a Flood upon the Old, Ungodly World, and Destroyed them; but saved <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Family, a Preacher of Righteousness.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:55696:11"/>
            <p>And after, in the New World, <hi>Nimrod</hi> got up and Built <hi>Babel.</hi> But the Lord confounded him, and his Followers. And after <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> run into Ungodliness, and Unlawful Deeds: and God turned them into Ashes. And after the Lord by his mighty Power, had brought the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> How soon did the Serpent sow his wicked Seed in them? And God gave them His Law, and His good Spirit to Instruct them; as in <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9.20. But they Rebelled against his Spirit, and turned their Backs against his good Law. And for their Disobedience, How often did the Lord suffer them to be carried into Captivity? And at last the Ten Tribes, for their Disobedience, by <hi>Salmonazer</hi> the King of <hi>Assyria,</hi> were carried away out of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> into Captivity, for their Disobeying and Rebelling against the Lord: And after the Two Tribes were carried away by the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> from <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was called the Glory of all Lands. And when the Lord Jesus Christ came, the Jews stopt their Ears, and closed their Eyes to Him and His Doctrine; and cryed, <hi>Away with Him, Crucifie Him, Crucifie Him.</hi> And Christ told them, their City should be compassed with Armies, and their Temple thrown down, and they should be scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered over all Nations; which came to pass by <hi>Titus</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> who Destroyed <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Temple, and scattered the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ews,</hi> that they could never Build <hi>Jerusalem</hi> nor the <hi>Temple</hi> since. And thus they were drove out of their own Land, for Disobeying God, and forsaking His Law and Spirit, like <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who were drove out of <hi>Paradice,</hi> for Disobeying God, and following the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Teaching, and forsaking of God's.</p>
            <p>And after Christ sent his Disciples to Preach the Gospel of Life and Salvation unto all Nations, and to every Creature under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: The Devil, he sowed his wicked Seed and Tares in the hearts of People, when they slept, and grew careless of God's Truth: and the Devil begat many Anti-Christs, false Prophets, false Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, false Apostles, Seducers and Deceivers, which got the form of Godliness, and the outward form of Christianity, and led ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after them, and so set up a false Church, the Whore, Mystery of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Mother of Harlots; who rid upon the Beast in the Dragons power, and made the Peoples, Nations and Tongues like Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: and in this VVhore, and false Church, is found th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood of the Prophets and Martyrs of Jesus: For <hi>John</hi> saith, <hi>She
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55696:12"/> was Drunk with the Blood of the Prophets and Martyrs of Jesus:</hi> that is with Heavenly <hi>Jerusalems</hi> Childrens Blood: For Heavenly <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> the Bride, the Lambs VVife, is the Mother of all the true Christians that Believe in the Light, and are Children of the Light, and receive Christ, who gives them Power to become the Sons of God. So this VVhore, or false Church, went from the true Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Heavenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and from Christ the true Husband; and become the Mother of Harlots, the Whore, that Drank the Blood of the Martyrs, and got upon the Persecuting Beast in the Dragons power; but the Judgment of the great Whore is come, and the Beast, Dragon, and false Prophet, <hi>John</hi> saw cast into the Lake of Fire, and the Everlasting Gospel Preached again to all Nations, Tongues and People, to settle them: and all that receive the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Gospel, the Seed, in which all Nations are Blessed, are Heavenly <hi>Jerusalems</hi> Children, and Children of the Seed, and are Children and Heirs of the Everlasting Kingdom of God and Christ, that stands in Power and Righteousness, and Joy and Peace in the Holy Ghost, and are of the New Creation in Christ Jesus: and this Seed shall be as the Sand of the Sea, and the Dust of the Earth, and the Stars of the Heaven, that cannot be Numbred: Christ saw his Seed, which are the Children of his Kingdom: <hi>He that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>JESUS CHRIST the same Yesterday, and to Day, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Heb. 13.8. who exercises his Prophetical Office, as he is a Heavenly Prophet; who opens Peoples Eyes, to see Spiritual and Heavenly things: and Christ their Saviour, who Redeems and Purchases them with his own Life, his Blood: and so Christ the Prophet, is to be heard in all things by his Children, who enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens every one that cometh into the VVorld; that in the Light they might see him, and hear him; and he openeth the Book of Conscience to them, and the Book of Life; that in it they may read and see their Names written there; which Book no man can open but Christ the Lamb.</p>
            <p>And Christ exercises his Office as a Heavenly Bishop, who rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses up his Children out of the Death in <hi>Adam,</hi> and makes them to sit together in the Heavenly Places in Christ Jesus; and he is a Bishop to over-see them, that they do not go out of the Heavenly Places in Him.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55696:12"/>
            <p>And Christ Exercises his Office, as a Heavenly Shepherd among his Spiritual Sheep, and feeds them with his Bread from Heaven, and Water of Life in his Heavenly Pasture, and his Sheep know his Voice, and follow him.</p>
            <p>And Christ Exercises his Office, as he is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; who Rules in the Hearts of his People by Faith, that they all may be one, saith Christ; as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us; and the Glory that thou gavest me, I have given them, that they may be one, even as we are one; I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in one: <hi>John</hi> 17.21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>So Christ, the Heavenly King and Lord, Rules, Orders, and Governs in the Hearts and Souls of his Children, who is the Bishop and chief Shepherd of the Soul to oversee and feed his Sheep.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>Concerning our Baptism.</head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith, there is one Baptism; <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.5. and by one Spirit, we are all Baptised into one Body; whether we be <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles;</hi> whether we be <hi>Bond</hi> or <hi>Free,</hi> and have been all made to Drink into one Spirit: So this is the one Spiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, which was set up above 1600 Years ago.</p>
            <p>And you may see more of the Distinction between <hi>John</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism and Christs; in my Book Entituled, <hi>A Distinction betwixt the two Baptisms, and the two Suppers of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How that <hi>John</hi>'s Baptism, with the Elements of Water did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and Christs Baptism, with Fire and the Holy Ghost doth encrease, who thoroughly purges his Floor, and burns up the Chaff with unquenchenable Fire; and how Christ gathereth the Wheat into his Garner; and this is our Baptism and Baptiser.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edmunton</hi>
                  <date>the 2d. <hi>Month,</hi> 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55696:13"/>
            <head>Postscript. <hi>The</hi> Antiquity <hi>of our</hi> Cross.</head>
            <p>THE Apostle saith to the Church of Christ, That the Preaching of the Cross is to them that perish, Foolishness; but unto us that are saved, it is the Power of God; <hi>1 Cor. 1.18.</hi> And such as were, and are Enemies to the Cross of Christ, were, and are Enemies to the Power of God: So all your Stone, Wooden, Brass, Silver or Gold Crosses, you have invented, and set up since the Apostles Days, is not the Cross of Christ, the Power of God; but the Works of your own Hands: And the Apostle saith, God forbid that I should Glory, save in the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the World was Crucified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and I unto the World; <hi>Gal. 6.14.</hi> So it was the Power of God, the Cross of Christ, the Apostle gloried in, by whom the World was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to him, and he unto the World; and this is our Cross, which we Glory in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was set up above <hi>1600</hi> Years: ago: And it is not like that it was, a Cross made of Wood, Stone, Iron, Brass, Silver, or Gold, that the Apostle, or the Church of Christ Gloried in; or that such outward, Temporal and Wordly Crosses, as Men make and invent, should Crucifie People to the World; that which Crucifies People to the World and the World to them, is the Cross of Christ, the Power of God, which Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, all are to bow down to, and their Faith is to stand in it: and they are Foolish and Dark, that think a Cross of Stone, Wood, Iron, Silver or Gold, which Man hath made; is the Cross of Christ, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God; and to bow to such Worldly Temporal Things, and call them the Cross of Christ, is contrary to the Scriptures, that the Apostles taught to the Church of Christ in their Days; and this was the Church of Christs Cross in the Apostles Days, and is the Church of Christs now: But they could not, nor can we bow to any Temporal outward worldly Cross, that M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n have made with their Hands, and bow down to them: For such as do Worship the Works of their own Hands, are Enemies to the Cross of Christ, the Power of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55696:13"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>